<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<Blogs>

<Blog>
<Title>PB Tracker Update</Title>
<Date>September 30, 2013</Date>
<Image>pbtracker-rggibson-093013.png</Image>
<Image>pbtracker-beavisbutthead-093013.png</Image>
<Image>pbtracker-submit-093013.png</Image>
<Image>pbtracker-viewall-093013.png</Image>
<Text><![CDATA[
<p>
A week has passed since I first posted about PB Tracker, so I figure it's time to post an update. 
I have had at least a few people mention something to me about the site, so it's good to hear that there is some interest in this project. 
</p>
<p>
PB Tracker still looks as grey as ever, but the site is much more functional than it was a week ago. 
Optional links to videos can now be added to runs. 
In addition, all runs submitted by a runner can be viewed and the owner of the runs can edit submissions at will. 
While the colour scheme may still be boring, I've also added appropriate box art to many of the pages. 
Since I'm wanting a site that at the minimum replicates <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/richardggibson/rggibson">my old Twitch TV personal best table</a>, box art was mandatory. 
</p>
<p>
Furthermore, there are now game pages that list every runner's personal best time for each run category. 
I dare say the word "leaderboard" here, but I guess that is kind of what these pages represent. 
Just to be clear, I am not trying to compete with SRL and their upcoming leaderboard. 
These game pages are only here for convenience, much like <a href="http://www.congratsio.com/game/mario-tennis/records">similar pages exist on Congratsio</a>. 
Runners' times will only appear on these game pages if the runners themselves submit their runs. 
For this reason, PB Tracker's game pages will be far from an accurate speedrunning leaderboard. 
I am actually excited to see what the SRL guys come up with as it sounds like they will be implementing a true leaderboard that will list the best run times with video links known for many games. 
</p>
<p>
I still have a number of things on my to-do list before I push the site live. 
This list includes the ability to delete previous runs, as well as a column that lists a runner's average time for any given game and category. 
User profiles are also very minimal at the moment. 
I would like to include links to a runner's Twitter, YouTube, and TwitchTV accounts on their PB page. 
It would be really cool to add the option to auto-tweet upon submission, but that certainly won't be available from the get-go. 
We'll see if I ever get to any such fancy features after deployment. 
</p>
<p>
That's all for now. 
Keep fit and have fun. 
</p>
]]></Text>
</Blog>

<Blog>
<Title>PB Tracker</Title>
<Date>September 23, 2013</Date>
<Image>pbtracker-front-092313.png</Image>
<Image>pbtracker-rggibson-092313.png</Image>
<Text><![CDATA[
<p>
A while back, I spent several hours creating <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/richardggibson/rggibson">an info page for my Twitch TV channel</a> that, among a few other things, tracks my personal best times for all the games I speedrun. 
It's just a simple, static html page generated from a spreadsheet and a couple dirty scripts. 
However, it takes a bit of effort to update and I have been meaning to improve the page for some time now. 
After taking <a href="https://www.udacity.com/course/cs253">Udacity's Web Development online course</a>, I feel like I have enough tools now to actually build something significantly better.  
</p>
<p>
To that end, I started developing a dynamic web app called "PB Tracker" to make it easier to record and display speedrun times in a simple, tabular format. 
I have included user signups, so the app will be available for anyone to use that may be interested in tracking their own runs. 
At first glance, you may notice that the site looks, well, very grey. 
This is because I have spent zero time on the actual appearance of the site and have only focused on functionality to this point. 
Also, if you are familiar with some of the other speedrunning sites around, you may also see some similarities here with both <a href="http://www.congratsio.com/">Congratsio</a> and <a href="https://forum.speeddemosarchive.com/post/speedrun_leaderboards_discussion_topic_srl.html">the SpeedRunsLive leaderboards plan</a>. 
In fact, the SRL guys were looking for some coding help, and I didn't volunteer to instead work on this. 
I feel a little guilty about that, but I feel the goals of PB Tracker are significantly different from Congratsio's and SRL's. 
</p>
<p>
Firstly, though the name of the site may be a bit misleading, the site is built to track <i>all</i> run times, not just PBs. 
One of the things I enjoy about speedrunning is setting goals and making progress towards those goals. 
Beating a PB is always a great goal, but sometimes that is a daunting task (at least for me). 
Instead, I like to think about beating my <i>average</i> time. 
So, by submiting every run, the site will track both average times and best times. 
Secondly, one of my stretch goals is to build a new split program that can automatically upload finished run times to PB Tracker, making the recording of times much more seamless. 
The split program will likely be quite simple and compatible with the <a href="http://www.mediafire.com/?llxj7i54wuxgi">WSplit</a> file format.  
I'm also planning to have splits recorded from other runners be downloadable for anyone to use.
</p>
<p>
On the tech side of things, I will be deploying the site through Google App Engine at the custom domain <a href="http://www.pbtracker.net">pbtracker.net</a> that I just registered this morning. 
I am developing in Python, using the latest version of <a href="http://getbootstrap.com">Twitter Bootstrap</a> and doing some html templating with <a href="http://jinja.pocoo.org/">jinja2</a>. 
I am not a web developer by any stretch of the imagination, so I will likely be doing some very foolish things along the way. 
I don't have a release date planned for PB Tracker just yet, but I do plan to release the site as soon as it is functional, even if all the features are not quite there yet. 
Stay tuned. 
</p>
]]></Text>
</Blog>

</Blogs>
