<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<Industry>

<Interest>
<ID>gamedev</ID>
<Title>Game Development</Title>
<Image>game-dev.png</Image>
<Details><![CDATA[
<p>
Video game development is perhaps the largest intersection of both my passion and expertise. 
Gaming has been a large part of my life and I spent many hours of my youth mastering several games of many genres. 
In fact, video games are what first led to my fascination of the complexities and possibilities of artificial intelligence. 
This fascination led me to the <a href="http://ualberta.ca">University of Alberta</a> and a Ph.D. studying <a href="academia?t=games">artificial intelligence and games</a>. 
Developing champion computer poker programs has not only opened my eyes to state-of-the-art artificial intelligence algorithms, but it has also vastly improved my technical programming skills, particularly in C and C++. 
</p>

<p>
I am very interested in applying my skills and expertise to create fun and innovative games. 
In particular, I am interested in joining or forming a small team of developers where I can have a large impact on both the technical and creative components, especially within gameplay and AI. 
While much of my career has been spent in academia, I did spend 8 months at <i>Propaganda Games</i>, a former Disney game studio in Vancouver. 
I joined the studio during preproduction of a Pirates of the Caribbean game that unfortunately was later cancelled. 
Nonetheless, I have experience in the industry and am enthusiastic towards returning to game development. 
</p>
]]></Details>
</Interest>

<Interest>
<ID>research</ID>
<Title>Industrial Research</Title>
<Image>gavel.png</Image>
<Details><![CDATA[
<p>
Research is a very rewarding line of work and I am interested in continuing my research career beyond academia. 
My Ph.D. work in artificial intelligence and computational game theory has applications beyond the poker table. 
The first examples that come to mind are those problems arising in industry that are simulated by the <a href="http://tac.sics.se/page.php?id=1">Trading Agent Competition</a>. 
For instance, Google runs ad auctions where companies place bids for top link positions in keyword searches. 
Such auction mechanisms lend themselves very well to a game-theoretic approach, much like the approach taken by successful computer poker agents. 
I am interested in extending my work in computer poker to other domains, including ad auctions and other game-like problems. 
Furthermore, I am very open to broadening my horizons and conducting research in other related domains, such as machine learning, mathematical modelling, and optimization. 
</p>
]]></Details>
</Interest>

<Interest>
<ID>startups</ID>
<Title>Startups</Title>
<Image>rubik.png</Image>
<Details><![CDATA[
<p>
A startup is a company that is built to grow rapidly. 
I am interested in founding or joining young startups in the technology sector located in Victoria, BC.
I believe in the methodology of hiring and partnering with smart, creative individuals that are superstars at what they do, be it on the engineering side or on the business side of things. 
My main areas of interest for a startup are in:
<ul>
<li>video games / indie game development</li>
<li>sports betting / e-gaming</li>
<li>poker training software</li>
<li>online reality gaming (eg. <a href="http://www.tengaged.com/">tengaged.com</a>)</li>
</ul>
</p>
]]></Details>
</Interest>

</Industry>
