<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<Sports>

<Project>
<Title>Tennis</Title>
<Image>andy-murray.jpg</Image>
<Details><![CDATA[
I only started playing tennis regularly in 2009, but it has quickly become one of my favourite sports to play. 
I have won a few singles tournaments and have been knocked out early in other tournaments, but I am about a 4.5-5.0 player. 
Other than an occasional hit on the wood courts at Savary Island, I have only ever played on hard courts, indoor and out. 
I also generally just play singles because I am trash at doubles. 
In addition, I enjoy watching professional tennis on TV with my favourite player being Andy Murray, pictured on the right.
]]></Details>
</Project>

<Project>
<Title>Hockey</Title>
<Image>habs.png</Image>
<Details><![CDATA[
While I am absolutely terrible at ice hockey, I played a lot of ball hockey throughout my youth and continue to play today. 
My favourite position is in goal, probably because I idolized Patrick Roy as a kid. 
I was also a fan of Curtis Joseph growing up and when I play, I wear a mask similar to his. 
I'm also a die-hard Montreal Canadiens fan. 
]]></Details>
</Project>

<Project>
<Title>Baseball</Title>
<Image>red-sox.png</Image>
<Details><![CDATA[
Although I have played little real baseball since graduating from Little League, I am still a big fan of the sport. 
However, I have kept up by playing slo-pitch every summer since my first year of university. 
I am also a big Red Sox fan and try to catch as many games that come on TV as I can. <br>
<br>
In the Spring of 2003, my friend Chris Lubinich and I coached a Minors Little League team at Layritz Park in Victoria.  
The kids were between 8 to 10 years old and were always enthusiastic about playing, which made coaching very easy and enjoyable.  
It was a fantastic experience and I look forward to having the opportunity to coach Little League again in the future. 
Great idea, Lubes!
]]></Details>
</Project>

<Project>
<Title>Soccer</Title>
<Image>lfc.png</Image>
<Details><![CDATA[
Soccer was the first organized sport that I played back when I was just 7 years old. 
I played all through elementary school and high school, but now only play occasionally. 
Likely thanks to my ball hockey experience, I enjoy playing goalkeeper more than any other position. 
I somewhat follow the English Premier League and my favourite team is Liverpool FC.
]]></Details>
</Project>

<Project>
<Title>Basketball</Title>
<Image>basketball.png</Image>
<Details><![CDATA[
Although I rarely play basketball these days, I did play for my high school teams at Colquitz Jr. Secondary School and Spectrum Community School in Victoria. 
Playing high school basketball was a lot of work, but also a lot of fun and I learned a lot from some great coaches. 
Since I'm not the biggest guy around, my entire game pretty much relied on being able to shoot the ball reasonably well. 
On the right is a picture of what I would look like if I could dunk. 
]]></Details>
</Project>

<Project>
<Title>Fishing</Title>
<Image>fishing.jpg</Image>
<Details><![CDATA[
I don't really know how to fish, but luckily I have friends that do. 
Typically we like to go catch some big salmon as seen in the photo on the right, where I am the furthest on the left. 
We also often trap for crabs and prawns and have had quite a bit of success fishing around Savary Island near Powell River, BC. 
]]></Details>
</Project>

</Sports>
