<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<VideoGames>

<Project>
<Title>Speedrunning</Title>
<Youtube_ID>AuYHnFvMnhg</Youtube_ID>
<Twitter></Twitter>
<Details><![CDATA[
A speedrun is a play-through of a game with the objective of completing the game as fast as possible. 
Speedrunning is currently one of my favourite hobbies. 
While most games are not designed with speedrunning in mind, speedrunning provides significant replayability to games that would otherwise be played only once or twice, particularly for the retro games I enjoy the most. 
I am an active member of <a href="http://speeddemosarchive.com">Speed Demos Archive (SDA)</a>, a site dedicated to hosting speedruns of the highest quality. 
SDA also strives to build a fun and friendly community around speedrunning and you can find me there under the screen name <a href="https://twitter.com/rggibson_">rggibson</a>. 
My primary speedrunning games are some of the classic Mega Man games on the original NES and the Wii, but I have also run some other random games. 
For example, the video on the right is my fastest playthrough of a match of <i>Bad News Baseball</i> on the NES, where I beat the CPU in 2 minutes and 32 seconds. 
I almost always stream my speedruns live on <a href="http://www.twitch.tv/rggibson/">Twitch TV</a> and a number of my better runs can be found on <a href="http://www.youtube.com/user/rggibson11">YouTube</a>. 
]]></Details>
</Project>

<Project>
<Title>Casual Gaming</Title>
<Image>nhl94.jpg</Image>
<Details><![CDATA[
When I'm not speedrunning, I enjoy playing other games at a more casual level.  
Many of my favourite games are sports titles, both old and new.  
Some of my particular favourites include <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blades_of_Steel">Blades of Steel</a> on the NES, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baseball_Stars>Baseball Stars</a> on the NES, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NHL_%2794">NHL 94</a> on the Sega Genesis (pictured on the right), and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mario_Tennis">Mario Tennis</a> on the N64. 
I especially enjoy playing these games with friends through head-to-head local play.    
Some of the newer games that I often play on the Playstation 3 are the NHL and MLB: The Show series. 
Finally, I own a small collection of NES baseball games, from both good games like Baseball Stars, to bad games like <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roger_Clemens'_MVP_Baseball">Roger Clemens' MVP Baseball</a>. 
]]></Details>
</Project>

</VideoGames>
